Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1800-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1916-1918 (Offsite-box 52, Volume 303.1)
  Is embossed "Photographs Vol. II," Angela as a baby, at Aratoma Farm, Katonah, views at a cottage in Summerville, S.C. plantation homes, cabins, a fort, unidentified African Americans, homes in Beaufort, S.C., snapshots at a wedding, views at Happy Valley Farm, including the gardens, family, building stone pump house, travels in Plattsburg, N.Y. and Stockbridge, Mass., Robert Fowler in uniform, R.O.T.C. training in Plattsburg, picnics and beach views, biplanes at a field in Garden City, L.I.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1919-1925 (Offsite-box 52, Volume 303.2)
  Fowler family snaphots, including children, babies, Godwin and other families; farm and garden scenes; Katonah Welcome Home parade, including World War I soldiers and nurses, floats, a band concert, May 31, 1919; views in Massachusetts including historic homes and buildings, and interiors; snow scenes; views in Connecticut and Rhode Island; horses; construction scenes; Rippowam School field day and play, 1923.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1921-1922 (Offsite-box 53, Volume 303.3)
  Fowler family snapshots, including children; trip to the Mediterranean, Spain, France, Italy, Monaco, England, including churches and cloisters, castles, chateaus, villas, cottages, gardens and street scenes; views in Rheims showing World War I destruction.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1925-1929 (Offsite-box 54, Volume 303.4)
  Hiking and hunting in Maine, blizzard of 1926 in Katonah, dogs and children, skating, sledding, etc.; other views at the Fowler home in Katonah, including tree house and bird feeder, Banksia roses, horseback riding; African American domestics Annie, Dorothy, and Ann Eliza; Waring family members and views in Charleston, and other S.C. locations; Rippowam School activities, including plays and field days; swimming, boating and beach views; Godwin family members, Godurie family members; vacation views in Florida, Massachusetts, Long Island, Rhode Island, Cuba; views of New Orleans; Whitman family members; Warren family members; gardens, including family working in garden and stacking firewood. See also album #89, 304-307.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1932-1936], 1932-1933 (Offsite-box 53, Volume 304.1)
  Snapshots of the Fowler Family, friends and relations; Rippowam School field days, St. Paul's School (Concord, N.H.) crew races; children playing, swimming, on the beach, sailing, and horseback riding; vacationing on Cape Cod, including group watching an eclipse of the sun through filters, and the sun during the eclipse; views in Katonah; horse-show at Bedford, N.Y.; winter and spring holidays, 1933, including sledding and other snowy scenes, playing field hockey, baseball and horse riding; birthday picnics.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1932-1936], 1934 (Offsite-box 53, Volume 304.2)
  Trip to Scotland and Ireland: castles, cottages, landscapes, gardens, family members; views at a regatta, a horse show and horse "Blood stock sale"; sheep dipping, peat cutters and other country scenes; beach scenes; Katonah.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1932-1936], 1935-1936 (Offsite-box 77, Volume 304.3)
  House, gardens, picnics, crew races, snow scenes, dogs; travels.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1932-1936], 1935-1936 (Offsite-box 78, Volume 304.4)
  France, including Mont St. Michel, Spain, Oct. 21-Nov. 18 1935, views of castles, churches, interiors of the Alhambra, views of gardens, map showing route they drove, clippings from 1936 regarding Civil War, and trapped American tourists.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1932-1936] (Offsite-box 86, Volume 304.5)
  Loose album pages, showing Fowler family at Katonah, and loose portraits of the family. See also album #89, 303, 305-307.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1936-1939], 1936, May-1937, May (Offsite-box 78, Volume 305.1)
  Fowler family activities including picnics, tennis, crew, field day, swimming, holidays, beach scenes, sailing, gardening, trips.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1936-1939] (Offsite-box 79, Volume 305.2)
  Activities including picnics, tennis, snow scenes, dogs, stacking firewood, working on the road, repairing pool; views in Williamsburg, Va., Bermuda; Philadelphia Garden Club outing, St. Paul's School, crew races, sailing, gardens, wedding of Angela Fowler and Craig Wylie; Shirley Temple on deck of Queen of Bermuda.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1936-1939] (Offsite-box 79, Volume 305.3)
  1939 trip including Italy, Greece, Turkey, views aboard ship. See also album #89, 303, 304, 306, 307.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1941-1945], 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 80, Volume 306.1)
  Fowler family activities, Robert Fowler, III in navy uniform, views in Quebec, Maine, Rhode Island, Pam at Smith College flying field; Christmas.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1941-1945], 1943 (Offsite-box 54, Volume 306.2)
  Grandchildren, including christenings.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1941-1945] (Offsite-box 55, Volume 306.3)
  Family activities, grandchildren; all vols. include some color photos. See also album #89, 303-305, 307.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951] (Offsite-box 55, Volume 307.1)
  One album, partially filled, no date, possibly 1946, views of people in yard at Katonah.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1946-1947 (Offsite-box 55, Volume 307.2)
  Children and grandchildren, skiing, yard work, swimming, fishing, a parade, beach scenes, picnics.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1947 (Offsite-box 81, Volume 307.3)
  Garden club picnic with women in historic costume, construction project, digging potatoes, family activities, including sailing.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1948 (Offsite-box 56, Volume 307.4)
  Pam's Wedding album, 1948: larger format professional photographs of the wedding of Pam Fowler to Robert McKim.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1948-1949 (Offsite-box 56, Volume 307.5)
  Engagement parties for Pam and Harry; snapshots of Pam's wedding, including color shots; family activities, Thanksgiving, horses in Virginia, color snapshots of the gardens at Katonah.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 81, Volume 307.6)
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1949 (Volume 307.7)
  Spring views in Katonah and elsewhere, children's homes, grandchildren, beach views.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951], 1950 (Offsite-box 56, Volume 307.8)
  Children and grandchildren, painting the chicken coop, attending a dog show, beach views, C.F. on sailboat with camera in her lap.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1946-1951] (Offsite-box 56, Volume 307.9)
  Fowler and Wylie Family at Fisher's Island, including beach scenes; McKim family with house, incluiding interior, automobile, and baby Charlotte; a wedding; men fishing, and fishing boats; includes color photographs. See also album #89, 303-306.
- [Album of images of women], [1895] (Offsite-box 82, Volume 308)
  Has a description of "A perfect woman" pasted on inside front cover; images of women, many taken from "Sarony's Living Pictures" published by Napoleon Sarony in 1895; includes views from other sources, including reproductions of sculpture and paintings.
- Photographs, 1901, 1898-1901 (Volume 309.1)
- Photographs, 1902, 1898-1902 (Volume 309.2)
  On the cover are earlier images. Primarily snapshots; portraits of Albert and Alma Clayburgh; Dewey Arch and Naval Parade, 1899; Central Park; house called the Crags in Harmony Park, Yonkers including interiors and porches, stables, greenhouse, gardens, dairy and chicken yard, carriages in stable, portraits of horses; Albert Clayburgh on porch at crags, and on board the yacht Coyote; snapshots of friends and family in garden, including terrier named Folly; views in Yonkers, including Getty Square, Warburton Ave., Broadway, Main Street, Van Cortland Road, churches, Manor House, the racetrack; views on the Hudson, including ferry landing at Alpine with Palisades, the old Cornwallace Headquarters, Hudson piers at Yonkers; residences and other buildings in Dobbs Ferry, Hastings, Irvington; Ardsley Gold Club; views in New Hampshire including hotels, mountains and waterfalls; views in Saratoga; ice sailing at Lakewood, N.J.; commercial photographs and snapshots of Paris, including views, from Exposition Universalle (?); Fontainbleau; Versaille; Nice, including self-portrait in convex glass; Villefrance; Monte Carlo; Mentone; Rome; Naples; snapshot of soldiers along side of road; Pompeii; goats and donkeys.
- [Album of photographs of Victorian resort homes], [1890] (Offsite-box 81, Volume 310)
  Albumen prints of country homes, children playing, a train stations with waiting omnibuses, and a view of an African American man; views of newly built homes, one still under construction; portrait of man with cigar; two views of surf; copy of a painting of a woman; man on horseback; portrait of a girl.
- [Albumen prints of Europe], [1890-1899] (Offsite-box 57, Volume 311)
  Views of Amsterdam, Brussels and other northern European cities.
- Princeton College, Class of '73, 1873 (Offsite-box 83, Volume 312)
  Individual portraits of faculty and of the class of 1873; group portraits of the class, young men playing cards, a group of work men including African American, group including man in costume, gymnasts; views of the campus, including building under construction, and train crossing a small draw bridge; interior view of library; copy of a cartoon showing student life; photographs by Howell, of N.Y.
- C. Davenport Clarke, Wesleyan University '78, 1878 (Offsite-box 57, Volume 313)
  Portraits of faculty and students of the class of 1878 of Wesleyan University, including individual and group portraits, portraits of the baseball team and the crew, views of the campus, including interiors, and views of Middletown, Conn.; Frank Forshew, of Hudson N.Y., photographer.
- Sketches of Fairmount Park / by S.S., 1875 (Offsite-box 57, Volume 314)
  Copyright 1875 by S. Spackman; photographic copies of drawings or prints showing scenes in Fairmount Park, Philadelphia.
- [Photographic copies of allegorical prints], undated (Offsite-box 78, Volume 315)
  Photographic copies of allegorical prints, many of women and children in domestic situations; also includes landscapes, romantic couples, animals. See also album #12, 85
- [Views of New York city], [1897] (Offsite-box 58, Volume 316)
  Views taken from King's New York Views, 1897, copy of which is laid in album; including buildings and business, including insurance companies and others; also has images of ships laid in.
- [Low Family photographs], 1889, 1899 (Offsite-box 58, Volume 317)
  President's carriage coming up Broadway, April 30, 1889 centennial celebration; ship under construction, buildings and homes in Brooklyn, warehouses and piers along the Brooklyn waterfront, tree lined street, two men on sailboat named Abiel Abbot Low, portrait of two men, watercolor landscapes; views from a trip west, including group on glacier at Glacier, ferry called the Oregon, logs splashing into river or pond at Castle Crag, Cal., Mt. Shasta], group portrait above rapids [Niagara]; photographs are various sizes, most mounted; included photographs by B.J. Smith of Brooklyn, A.H. Green, Castle Crag, and Moorehead. See also album #24.
- [Allegorical subjects: original engravings for Godeys Lady's Book, Graham's Magazine, Peterson's Magazine and other sources], [1830-1869] (Offsite-box 58, Volume 318)
  Portraits, landscapes, allegorical scenes, Biblical illustration and genre scenes from various 19th century publications; most laid in album as if the owner had intended to mount them in the album.
- H. B. Lawrence, Class '66, Bowdoin [College], 1866 (Offsite-box 59, Volume 319)
  Views of the college, professors and their homes, group portraits of class and fraternities, portraits of individual classmates, with later portraits of many of them laid in, view of Main Street, Brunswick, Me.
- Caricature Aus. dem Amerikanischen Bürgerkriege, [1860-1869] (Offsite-box 59, Volume 320)
  Print and photo montage caricatures on cartes-de-visite.
- [Murray family album, James B. Murray, 1789-1866], [1860-1879] (Offsite-box 61, Volume 321)
- [Album belonging to John B. Murray (1818-1889) and his wife Mrs. John B. Murray (Sara E. Crafts)], undated (Offsite-box 60, Volume 322)
  Cartes-de visite of celebrities, prominent people, family and friends, a group portrait of the Oneida Community.
- [De Groot family album], [1870-1920] (Offsite-box 60, Volume 323)
  de Groot family and others, including snapshots. See also album #33.
- Gramercy Park, 1831-1931 (Offsite-box 58, Volume 324)
  Album of items commemorating the Centenary of Gramercy Park, including clippings describing exhibit at the National Arts Club, a checklist of the exhibit, photographs documenting the exhibit, including people involved and descendants of those pictured; photographs of the park and surrounding area; parade of people in historic costume, going to the garden party May 16, 1931, some of the descendants of Alexander M. Lawrence, trustee of the Park..
- White Mountain views. -- [Boston, Forbes Co., 1884] (White Mountain series.) (Offsite-box 62, Volume 325)
  A collection of 15 Albertype prints. Issued in portfolio; views of Crawford House, railroad in White Mountain Notch, rivers and waterfalls, Mt. Washington, a log home on the Glen Ellis River, the Wiley home.
- Rangeley Lake Views. Forbes Co., [1890-1899] (Offsite-box 62, Volume 326)
  Gravures of Rangeley Lake and vicinity, including views of lakes, waterfalls, cottages, hotels, dams, camp, tourists with guns and fishing poles, Rangeley City, and Oquossoc Angling Assn. Building.
- Union College class of 1860 (Offsite-box 61, Volume 327)
  74 photographs of the class and of faculty, many with signatures; program for Alumni Day, 114th Commencement, 1910 laid in.
- Compliments of The Equitable Life Assurance Society of the U.S., [1903] (Offsite-box 82, Volume 328)
  Portraits of officers of the Equitable Life Assurance Society of the U.S., most dated 1903; one portrait of Henry B. Hyde notes that he died in 1899; others pictured include James W. Alexander, James Hazen Hyde, Gage E. Tarbell, George T. Wilson, William H. McIntyre, William Alexander, Thomas D. Jordan, Sidney D. Ripley, Bainbridge Colby, H.R. Winthrop, M. Murray, --- Van Cise, Robert De Forrest, Edward N. Lambert, M.D., Dr. Curtis, Dr. Bross, Dr. Pell, --- Jackson, --- Maine, August Belmont; photographic copy of letter from Hyde in 1859 regarding the founding of the Equitable, and offering a policy, and an advertisement listing the officers in 1899, laid in.
- [Views in Great Britain], [1880-1889] (Offsite-box 85, Volume 329)
  Views in Scotland, some dated between 1887 and 1889, including views of Kirn, the S.S. Ivanhoe, Rothsay Castle, the Trossachs, Loch Katrine, Loch Lomond, including swans on the Loch, Invarrary Cross, sculptures of Longfellow and Sir Walter Scott, views in Stratford, including interior of house and church, Warwick Castle, Kenilworth, Manor House Hotel, boats on river or canal, Canterbury Cathedral, windows in New College Chapel, Oxford, interior of Westminster Abbey, view of St. Paul's; view of a fjord; photographs by James Valentine and George Washington Wilson.
- [Clippings of articles by Marie Trommer], [1920-1959] (Offsite-box 86, Volume 330)
  Clippings of poems, essays, reviews and translations by, and mentions of Marie Trommer, many of them on Jewish artists and subjects, and observations of life in Brooklyn.
- Photographs, 1859, C.P. Bailey [Dartmouth College Class of 1859] (Offsite-box 83, Volume 331)
  Most images signed on mount, many with accompanying dedication laid in.
- [de Loosey and Havemeyer family album], [1860]-1916 (Offsite-box 84, Volume 332)
  Portraits of the de Loosey and Havemeyer families: Emilie de Loosey became Mrs. Theodore A. Havemeyer; includes copy photographs of paintings and earlier photographs, engravings, and tintypes; Charles de Loosey with Carlotta, wife of Emperor Maximillian of Mexico at Niagara Falls; portraits of Frederick C. Havemeyer, Augustus Havemeyer, John and Lily Havemeyer Mayer, Emily (Mayer) Willis in her wedding gown posed in front of wall of large leaves with her dog, E.C. Potter with his polo mallet and with family, including Emily Havemeyer Potter, Bianca Duncan and children; F.C. Havemeyer IV and friend in Japanese costume drinking tea; includes photographs by Alman, Marceau, Kamamura, Pach Bros., Reutlinger, Rilf and others.
- [Album of postcards, clippings and photographs], [1907] (Offsite-box 84, Volume 333)
  Postcards from around the world, including the U.S., Philippines, Japan, Egypt, Ceylon, Monte Carlo; portraits of William Williams, Sam W. Hoke,; snapshots of the Hotel Bonhomie, a fishing boat; clippings about fishing, presidential candidates, bill posting, lodge officers, City Island, circus history, and obituaries of Tammany politicians and circus people; ticket for 1907 Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show.
- [European celebrities, cartes-de-visite], [1850-1880] (Volume 334)
  List of sitters laid in.
- Harvard, 1858 (Volume 335)
  Views of the campus, faculty, including Louis Agassiz, Asa Gray, Oliver Wendell Holmes, James Russell Lowell, Henry W. Longfellow and others, and members of the class of 1858; letter from Geo. C. Burgess, member of the class to H. W. Bryant, bookseller, laid in.
- Smaller World War etchings, 1920 / Bernhardt Wall (Offsite-box 62, Volume 336)
  Signed and numbered on title page; plates mounted on inside of covers; also includes a color sketch of a soldier.
- Grand Winter Cruise of S.S. La Touraine to the Mediterranean, the Orient and the Holy Land, [1895] (Offsite-box 62, Volume 337)
  Issued in portfolio with title page; Compagnie Générale Transatlantique, French Line, publisher; 102 leaves; views of the ship, crew on deck, passengers on deck; views in New York, Spain, France, Italy, Malta, Greece, Alexandria, Cairo, the Pyramids, Constantinople, Jaffa, Jerusalem, in the Suez Canal, Tunis and Algiers.
- Scrapbook, "Natalie Lorillard Bailey, Started September 1st 1907", [1890]-1929 (Offsite-box 85, Volume 338)
  Mrs. Lewis Gouverneur Morris; includes views from the 1890s-1929, family and friends, and including costume balls and plays.
- Centennial Year, 1959-1960, Cooper Union (Offsite-box 86, Volume 339)
  Photographs, programs, photostats of articles and other materials documenting the Centennial of Cooper Union. Issued in slip case.
- [Photographs of Equitable Bldg.], undated (Volume 340)
  Views of building, George B. Post, architect; exterior view, ornate entrance hall, with murals and stained glass vaulted ceiling, board room, executive offices, including man in office, stairway and column-line hallway, stained glass, office with high tables for clerks, cashiers'' office, "Negro elevator starter (very tall)" showing African American man in hallway, office with stuffed owl on top of safe, Law Library, "Primitive Pent House on the roof," luncheon room for Board of directors (after meeting), men seated at tables in entry hall.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of James Hazen Hyde, 1946.
- Reise-Erinnerungen, 1885-86, 1888, 1885-1886, 1888 (Volume 341)
  Nord-Amerika und Canada, 1885-1886; Spanien, 1888; Commercial photographs and published views in North American and Spain, including views of yachts, probably at Newport, hotels, homes, tourists at Niagara Falls, views at Savannah, group with horses and dogs for a hunt, views in Jacksonville, snowy views and ice palaces (St. Paul?), huge stacks of lumber by river, government buildings; Montreal; views in Spain, including Bilbao, Toledo, Seville, the Alhambra, Cartagena.
- [George Cotton's Theater Scrapbook], [1924-1966] (Volume 342)
  Playbills, reviews and other articles, telegrams, snapshots and theater stills documenting the career of George Cotton, many of the earlier items showing set designs by Norman Bel Geddes.
- [Portrait album], [1870-1899] (Volume 343)
  Portraits of mostly unidentified persons, including many of young children and women; one portrait of woman with seven St. Bernard puppies; mostly studio, some outdoor views; includes some identified as with the name Lewis.
- [Photographs of the New York city water system], [1900]-1908 (Offsite-box 62, Volume 344)
  Views in Lower Manhattan of laying new water mains, and firemen testing the pressure at the Gansevoort pumping station; loose photographs of the New York waters system, including Croton Reservoir.
- Old New York, undated (Volume 345)
  Photographs by H.H. Tiemann Co., Peyser & Patzig, and unidentified photographer(s) depicting New York scenes, including Delmonico's Hotel (1885), Madison Avenue, north from 41st (1884), Fifth Avenue north from 18th, with Chickering Hall (1879); Fifth Avenue South from 34th St. (1899); Fifth Avenue south from 35th Street (1876, 1898); Dr. Sarsaparilla Townsend House, 34th and 5th, site of Stewart Mansion (1880); A.T. Stewards House (March 17, 1894); Astor House, (1893, 1894); Fifth north from 34th (1899); 37th and Fifth Ave. (1908); Lord & Taylor, 38th and Fifth (1907); Old Reservoir (1899); Rutgers Female college from 41st (1885); Fifth Ave. and 42nd Street (after 1911); Fifth Ave. State (1899); Fifth Avenue North from 42nd Street (1899); Jewish Synagogue, Fifth Ave. and 44th; N.E. corner Fifth Ave. and 45th showing John N. Golding's office (1907); Windsor Hotel, Fifth Ave. and 46th (1894; Fifth Avenue North from 48th (1899); Buckingham Hotel, Fifth Avenue & 50th Street (1878); North side West 48th, (1922, later Rockefeller Center); Democratic Club, Buckingham Hotel and Belgravia, Fifth and 49th St. (1907, later Saks); North east corner Fifth Ave. and 51st, Union Club (1938); Twin Vanderbilt Houses, Fifth and 52nd, and looking south on Fifth from 52nd (1925); Madison Ave. looking Northwest from 55th (with much open land in foreground); West side of Fifth Ave. 53rd to 55th Street (1890); Fifth Ave. north from 53rd (1898); St. Thomas Church, Fifth Ave. and 54th St. (1876); St. Luke's Hospital, Main entrance, Fifth Avenue and 54th; St. Luke's looking east toward Fifth Ave. (1894); Mrs. Alice G. Vanderbilts, 57th to 58th, and Fifth Avenue; Plaza Hotel, Fifth Ave. and 59th (1894); Fifth Ave. & 61st Street, Hotel Pierre (1930); Temple Beth El, Fifth Ave. and 76th (1892); N.E. corner, Fifth Ave. and 82nd, showing empty lot, shack and women (1898); Fifth Ave. and 101st-102nd St., (1894) showing shacks; S.E.. corner, Madison Ave. and 28th (1911); Park Avenue Hotel (1875); Fourth Ave. and 42nd St. showing destroyed building (1896); Park Avenue North from 60th St.; Madison 49-50, Columbia College; N.E. corner 49th and Madison, Hamilton Hall; Gerry House and Metropolitan Club, 60th and 61st S. (1930); Park Ave. North from 66th St.; Hunter College, Park Ave. 68th - 69th, with piles of stone lining street; looking west from park Ave. and 93rd (1872); Sutton Place 56th Street looking N.E. (1910); Shot tower, Sutton Place, 53-54 St. (1874); New York Athletic club; York Avenue East side looking south, 63rd-62nd (1948); Racquet and Tennis Club, 25 West 43rd. St.; Central Park Garden, 6th Ave. and 59th (1883); Rossmore Hotel, 42nd and Broadway (1882); Broadway n. from 42nd (1901); On the Boulevard (Broadway) (1898); Hon. D. F. Tiemann's house, Broadway and 98th (1898); 80-81st St. and West End Ave. (1894); Broadway west from 123rd (1903); New York Central Yards looking north (1904); N.Y. Central Yard looking s. west from about 47th (1898); Park Avenue S. from 50th Street (1903); e. sided Park Ave., 50-51st looking south to site of Waldorf & Park Lane (1921); New York Central Train Yard, Park Ave. s., (1898); Fifth Ave., 10th and 11th (190s); copy of painting showing Beekman Cove on East River.